大家好，我是A. Jesse Jiryu Davis
Hi, I'm A. Jesse Jiryu Davis
我将解释Python协程是如何工作的
and I'm going to tell you how Python coroutines work.
介绍一下我自己
Little about me,
我是MongoDB的一名高级工程师，职责是为MongoDB写Python和C的驱动。
I work for a MongoDB,I'm a staff engineer, there work on the Python and the C drivers for MongoDB.
是的,我们正在招聘。我强烈推荐来MongoDB工作
Yes, we are hiring and I highly recommend working for MongoDB.
访问bit.ly/mongo-jobs了解所有的工作机会
You can go to Mongo-jobs to see all of the jobs that we've got open.
如果你想了解更多关于这个话题的信息
And if you want more information about this talk,
我在bit.ly/coroutines中新增了一个页面
I've set up a landing pages at bit.ly/coroutines
你可以在链接里找到本视频的代码
You can find links there to the code that I'm going to write right now,
同时，在即将发布的《开源应用程序架构》书中
and also to a chapter in the upcoming architecture of open source applications book
我和Guido(Python创始人)合著了一章，其中深入地阐述了python协程工作的细节
that I co-wrote with Guido Van Rossum that goes into far more depth and is a very detailed exposition of python coroutines work.
这个示例的主题是
So the agenda for this demo is going to be a
基于回调的异步框架
callback-based async framework,
写完之后，我们会看到它非常有效，但也有些混乱
and once we've written that we're going to see that it's very efficient but also kind of a mess,
所以我们最后要把它改写成一个基于协程的框架
and so we're going to adapt that to a coroutine based framework instead.
因此 从一个基于回调的异步框架入手
So to begin with a callback based async framework,
它使用非阻塞socket
It uses non-blocking sockets.
使用回调函数
uses the callbacks,
当然
of course,
它还使用一个事件循环
and it also uses an event loop.
至于协程
And as for coroutines,
到时候再说吧
well, we'll cross that bridge when we come to it.
编码之前有一些准备工作
So a little bit of setup,
我写了一个简单的web服务器(Github代码中的server.py)
I've written a simple web server and.
它可以响应http请求
It can respond to an HTTP request.
我为本地的python会议"PyGotham 2015"写了这篇文章
I wrote this for a local python conference PyGotham 2015,
所以你可以看到它向所有那些了不起的人们致意
so you can see that it says hello to all of the incredible people there.
这个框架的另一个有趣之处是它有点慢
And the other interesting thing about this framework is its kind of slow.
这个web服务器返回非常简单的响应
This web server returns very simple response,
但我故意增加了一些sleep代码 所以要花差不多一秒的时间响应
but I've coded it so that it takes almost a second to reply.
这么做的重要性将会在后面体现
And so that's going to end up being very important,
因为这是最适合用异步优化的场景：
because that's the sort of thing that async is optimized for.
与速度较慢的服务器或者客户端进行有效率的通信
Is for talking too slow servers or slow clients efficiently.
让我们看看
So let's see,
我们怎样才能以典型的python方式获取URL
how would we fetch a URL in the kind of typical python way.
所以我们先导入socket
so we would need to import socket right?
然后
And?
绑定到合适的域名和端口
Connected to the proper domain and port.
格式化一个请求
we format a request
把它发送到服务器
then we would send it to the server.
我用的python3环境
And I'm going to do this in Python 3
所以对那些通过网络传输的所有内容进行编码是很重要的
and so it's important to encode everything that we're going to send over the wire.
哦
Oh,
另一个需要记住的重要的事情是
and the other important thing to remember is that.
每个HTTP请求头部以两个回车换行符分隔
Each HTTP requests end in a double carriage return to a new line
所以一旦我们发送了请求就会收到响应 它会以分块的形式返回给我们
so once we've sent the request were going to receive the response and that'll come back to us in chunks.
所以我们要把它们收集到一个列表中
so we're just going to collect those in a list.
收集最多1000个分块(口胡)
Receive them up to a thousand chunks
一次接收1000字节
a thousand bytes at a time,
只要我们接收完一个分块
and as long as we've got a chunk.
就将它加到列表中，如果我们得到一个空的块
will append it to the list and if we get an empty chunk,
我们就知道服务器断开了
then we know that the server is hung up on us.
所以数据就接收完毕了
so our reception is complete,
所以响应内容将会是
and so the body is going to be....
我们将用空字节类型来连接所有的块
We'll use the empty bye to join all the chunks.
然后我们会解码
And then we'll decode that.
默认是utf-8
The utf-8 by default.
然后我们把响应内容的第一行打印出来
And then let's just prints the first line of the body.
所以
So,
因为我们在死循环中
and since we're in an infinite loop,
我们需要返回
we need to return,
这就是我们的get函数。如果我们get参数/foo
so that's our get function and if we get that path Foo
运行程序,可以看到响应的第一行是http 200 OK
and if I run this, you'll see that the first line of the response is an http 200 OK.
然后
And?
让我们看看
Let's also see.
整个过程的运行时间
How long that took
这需要大约一秒钟的时间 因为还有Python解释器的一点开销
So it takes about a second because there's a little bit of overhead in the Python interpreter.
这种方法的问题是 如果我们想要访问两个url
the problem with this approach is that if we want to get 2 Urls,
就需要两秒钟 因为我们是串行地获取URL
it's going to take two seconds because we get them serially.
典型方法是在两个线程上启动这两个get操作
And the typical approach to this might be to launch these two operations on two threads,
但如果我们等待数百个缓慢的请求，效率可能会变得非常低
but that might become inefficient if we're waiting for hundreds of slow requests,
因为我们不得不为这些请求创建数百个线程
and we have to spawn hundreds of threads for them.
有很多的开销是不必要的
There's a lot of overhead though it's not necessary,
所以我们将尝试写一个异步的框架来代替它
so we're going to try out making an async framework to do it instead,
这样我们就不需要为了执行数百次缓慢的I/O请求而创建数百个线程了
so that we don't have to spawn hundreds of threads in order to do hundreds of slow i/o operations,
我们想要比这更有效率的办法
we want to be more efficient than that.
所以
So.
异步框架可以使用非阻塞socket，python中实现非阻塞的基本框架非常简单
A async framework could uses non-blocking sockets and in python making socket non blocking is very simple.
如果我们运行程序，将会发生什么
Now what's going to happen if we run this?
我们会得到一个异常，因为
We're going to get an exception because.
一个非阻塞socket的意思是任何会阻塞的操作
A non blocking socket what that means is any operation that would block,
就像连接操作，要么立即成功 要么抛出异常
like connecting,either succeeds immediately or raises an exception.
对
Right.
它是不允许阻塞的
It's not allowed to block.
不允许一直等待直到程序成功完成操作
it's not allowed to wait for success.
所以我们需要一些方法来等待它完成
So we need some way to wait for that to complete.
我们用Python来做这个
And the way we do that in Python.
嗯
Well,
首先
first of all,
我们可以先忽略这个错误
we can just ignore that error.
但这没有太大帮助
But that's not going to get us very far
一旦我们试着给socket发送数据，就会报错：socket未连接
because as soon as we tried to send something of the socket is going to say that it's not connected yet right
当我们调用connect时
because when we called connect,
非阻塞socket开始执行操作
the non-blocking socket began the operation.
但它并没有等待操作完成
But it didn't wait for the operation to complete.
因此我们还没有准备好发送数据
And so we're not ready to send it yet.
那么，我们怎么知道何时才能准备好发送一个操作呢
So how do we know when we're ready to send an operation?
嗯
Well,
python3
python 3.
有一个易于使用的包叫做selectors
There's this handy module called selectors.
在每一个远古版本的操作系统中
In every operating system since time immemorial,
就有一些方法可以在非阻塞socket上等待某些事件
there has been some way to wait for some event on a non blocking socket.
最初
Originally,
有系统调用select
there was the system call select,
随着时间的推移
and then over time,
越来越多的可扩展的新版select已经被发明出来了
more and more scalable versions of select have been invented.
比如Linux上的poll
Like poll on Linux,
BSD和Mac上的epoll以及windows上的kqueue
epoll on Bsd and Mac kqueue on windows.
这些都是I/O完成端口
there's these I/O completion ports.
Python3.4的优点是
The nice thing about Python 3.4
你可以获取一个默认选择器
Is that you can just ask it for a default selector,
它会识别你当前使用的系统，给你最匹配的selector
and it will figure out what your running and give you the most efficient selector for your platform,
所以我们要做一个这样的程序：
so we'll make one of those and.
在我们试着给socket发送任何东西之前
Before we try to send anything on the socket.
我们将等待它到可读状态
We're going to wait for it to be readable.
我们会等着它准备好要发送的内容
We're going to wait for it to be ready for something to be sent,
为了做到这一点
so to do that,
我们注册了socket文件号
we register the sockets file number,
就是一个整型
which is just an integer.
它只是一个文件描述符
it's just a file descriptor.
这将告诉selector，这是一个我们在事件发生时关注的文件号
And we're going to tell the selector that this is a file number that we're interested in events on
我们关注的事件则是socket何时处于可写状态
and the specific event that we're interested in is we want to know when the socket is writable
pycharm可以自动为我们导入那个常量(win: Alt+Enter)
and pycharm can auto import that constant for us.
我们要做的下一件事是
The next thing we do
到目前为止，所做的一切都表明我们关注这个事件中的文件描述符
so all we have done so far said I'm interested in this event on this file descriptor.
如果我们调用select 它会等待我们要求的事件发生
And then if we call select that will wait for some event that we've asked about to happen.
所以
So,
一旦这种情况发生
once that happens,
我们可以注销文件号
we can unregistered the file number.
此时
And by this point.
s(socket)是可写的
s is writable.
这意味着我们可以合法地调用send
So that means that we can legally now call send on it.
如果我现在调用这个
So if I call this now.
你会看到程序已经越过这行
You'll see that I get past this line,
但是现在这里抛出一个异常，因为这个socket是可写的
but now we're throwing an exception down here because the socket is writable,
但是它还没有变得可读 我们还没有等待服务器开始发送它的响应
but it hasn't become readable yet We haven't waited for the server to start sending its response.
所以为了等待服务器
So in order to wait for that,
我们必须再做一次同样的操作
we have to do the same dance again,
这一次我们对可读情况感兴趣而不是可写情况
and this time we're not interested in write ability we're interested in readability.
这里可以用pycharm的自动导入（win: Alt + Enter）
So we have the pycharm auto inputs that
再次等待socket
We wait for it again,
一旦这个调用完成
and once this call completes,
那我们就注销文件号
then we'll unregistered the file number,
现在我们可以接收数据了
and now we're allowed to receive
如果我现在运行，它可以正常工作
so if I run this code now it completes,
但我们还没有得到真正想要的效果，还是需要两秒
but we haven't really won anything right still took two seconds.
我们只是把代码弄得一团糟
We just kind of made a small mess in our code.
但我们还没有获得任何效率的提升
But we haven't gained any efficiency improvements yet.
那么下一步做什么呢
So what's the next step?
在使用了非阻塞socket之后的步骤
The next step after we've started to use non blocking sockets,
是回调
is callbacks.
我将解释它是如何工作的
So I'll explain how that works.
回调是一种允许多个操作并发等待I/O操作的方法
Callbacks are a way of allowing multiple operations to be waiting concurrently for i/o operations.
首先以这个get函数为例
To begin with, this get.
当开始连接时
When it starts connecting,
一旦socket可写时，注册的回调将被执行
it needs to register callback to be executed once the socket is writable,
之后它需要返回
and then it needs to return
这样当我们在等待连接这个socket的时候，就可以开始获取另一个URL
so that work can begin on getting the other URL while we're waiting to connect this socket right,
我们需要某种并发手段来优化这两秒的时间
we need some sort of concurrency in order to get past this two seconds.
我们来看看它是如何工作的
So let's see how that would work.
我们可以先写回调的主体
We can begin by writing the body of that call back,
所以我将它命名为connected函数
so I'm gonna call it connected.
这将会执行
This is going to execute.
一旦socket已连接，它就会执行下一步
Once the socket is connected and it's going to do the next step.
但问题是
But the problem is,
你可以看到PyCharm有错误提示了
you can see that right now PyCharm is sort of losing its mind
因为在这个新函数中有两个变量没有声明，因为我们在get函数中创建了它们
because there's two variables that are not bound in this new function because we created them up here in get.
这两个变量是s和request
And the two variables are s and request.
假设这些变量通过某种方式传递给connected函数
So let's say that those are passed into connected somehow.
解决办法是
And that somehow is going to be.
我们将使用lambda来创建一个闭包来捕获这两个值
We're going to use a lambda to create a closure to capture those two values.
所以我们要创建一个Lambda表达式
so we'll create a Lambda.
这样调用Lambda执行connected函数就可以使用这两个变量了
And we'll say that calling the Lambda executes connected with the socket and the request,
我们把这个叫做lambda回调
and we'll call this lambda callback.
现在我们如何使用这个回调？
Now what do we do with this callback?
selector.register
Well selector.register,
它有特别的隐藏参数，有点像*b-side(唱片的B面，指没被选入专辑的歌)
it has this special hidden argument sort of a b-side,
它被称为data
and it's called data,
所以我们要把回调作为data的参数传递给调用者
so we're going to pass the callback again as data.
因为这是Python(动态语言)
because this is Python,
data可以是任何东西，所以我们要把lambda作为data参数传入
The data can be anything so we're going to pass in our lambda as the data.
然后
And?
我们要等到connected被调用时才注销那个文件号
We're going to wait until connected is called to actually unregistered that file number.
现在
Now,
如果我们这样做
if we do this.
不幸的是
Unfortunately,
我们实际上并没有完成任何工作
we don't actually get any work done.
因为我们的回调从来没有真正执行过
Because our callback is never actually executed.
那么我们如何确保在等待的事件发生的时候，立即执行这个回调呢
So how do we make sure that this callback is actually run, once the event that it's waiting for has been executed?
为了解决这个问题，我们需要异步框架的第三部分
Well for that we need the third part of our async framework.
我们需要一个事件循环
We need an event loop.
我在这里把它写出来
so I'm going to code that down here.
get函数将首先运行，它会启动一个socket连接
get is going to run first and it's going to start a socket connecting,
然后它会注册一个回调 当socket是可写的时候就会执行
and then it's going to register a callback to be executed when the socket is writable.
一旦foo执行完成了，bar也做同样的操作
and once foo has done that it returns and bar does the same thing.
现在我们有两个非阻塞的socket在连接的过程中
So now we've got to two non blocking sockets that are open and in the midst of connected,
它们都已经在selector中注册了
and they've both been registered with the selector.
所以我先运行一个简略的事件循环
So I'm going to run a *dirt simple little event loop here,
写下selector.select
and it's going to say selector dot select.
现在让我们用调试器运行到这里，看看select实际返回的是什么
Now let's run this through the deBugger here and see what select actually returns.
所以我设置了一个断点
So I set a break point,
现在我们有了这个事件列表
and now we've got this events list,
如果我查看这个事件列表
and if I inspect that,
你会看到它是一个列表
you'll see that it's a list.
它有两个元素
It's got two elements,
我们来看看第一个元素是什么
and let's see what that first element is.
它有
It's got.
它是一个有两个值的元组
It's a tuple with two values.
第二个值不是很有趣
A second value isn't very interesting.
这只是我们一开始传递的mask
This is just the *mask that we passed in at first,
它等于常量EVENT_WRITE的值
and it's equal to the EVENT_WRITE value.
但我们已经知道了 因为那是我们唯一感兴趣的事件
but we already knew that because that was the only event that we were interested in.
它是元组的第一个元素
It's this first element of the tuple.
这个SelectorKey很有趣
This SelectorKey thing that's really interesting,
当我调用寄存器时 你会看到我传递的数据值
and you'll see that the data value that I passed in when I called register.
在这个事件列表中得到了这个对象，它的内容是我注册为回调的lambda表达式
We're getting that back out in this events list and its contents is that lambda that I registered as the callback
让我们执行它
So let's execute it.
写一个循环
So for event.
And mask events.
Mask是我们不关心的东西
Mask is the thing we don't care about.
它的值是2
its too.
它等于常量EVENT_WRITE的值
It's equal to EVENT_WRITE
但是这个事件
but this event here.
它的数据字段是我们之前注册的回调
Its data field is the callback that we originally registered
所以我要叫它cb
so I'm going to call that cb,
然后调用它
and then I'm just going to call it.
现在运行程序,看看会发生什么 这样就可以进入函数内部(F7)
So if I run this now instead of breakpoint here and see what happens so it can step in.
你会发现我们进入这个lambda表达式
And you'll see that we step into this lambda here.
而lambda调用connected函数，这个函数的参数有socket和request
And the lambda calls connected and connected is executed with the socket and the request,
request的值是GET /foo
which is get foo
我们运行这个
So we run this.
我们需要在这里做同样的转换
We'll see that we need to do the same transformation down here for s.recv.
我们来修改一下
So let's do that.
我们可以说
And we can say.
回调
The callback.
因为当socket是可读时
For when the socket is readable,
将函数命名为readable
we're going to call it readable
和connected函数需要接收参数的方式是一样的
and the same way that connected needed to take the variables that had been available in the previous callback as arguments so does readable
在这个函数中仍然需要socket参数
in this case still needs the socket.
它不需要请求 我们已经完成了
It doesn't need request we're done with that,
但它确实需要一个分块的列表
but it does need the list of chunks.
所以它会把这两个作为参数
So it's going to take those two as arguments,
当它被执行时
and when it's executed,
它知道s在这个时候是可读的
it knows that s is readable by this time.
所以它可以注销它的文件描述符并接收一个分块
So we can unregister its file descriptor and receive a truck.
我们知道这个分块
And we know that a chunk.
嗯
Well,
我们知道这不会引发异常 因为select调用
we know that this won't raise an exception because the select call.
在这里确保了我们在这个socket上等待的事件都准备好了
Down here said that whatever we're waiting for on this socket is ready.
所以这里不会出现资源不可用或其他异常
So we won't throw a resource unavailable or whatever that exception was.
数据块要么包含一些内容 或者服务器已经关闭
The chunk will either contain something or if the server has closed,
那么这个分块就是空的
the connection then chunk is empty.
我们知道我们已经传完数据了
And we know that we're done.
在这里
So up here,
这意味着我们不调用select
that means that we don't call select,
因为这是事件循环的工作
because that's the eventloop's job,
但我们确实需要创建回调
but we do need to create the callback.
它和我们之前创建的回调非常相似
So it's going to be very similar to the callback that we created before
还是一个由lambda表达式创建的闭包
it's going to be a closure expressed by lambda,
当我们执行它的时候
and when we execute it.
我们要传入socket和chunks变量
We're going to pass it the socket and the chunks,
这不再是一个循环
and this is no longer a loop.
我们只是注册
We just register.
回调一次 然后我们就做完了
The callback once and then we're done.
这意味着
And that means that,
既然我们没有死循环了
since we no longer have a while true loop
如果在这里我们有分块
that down here, if we have a chunk,
我们需要等待剩下的部分
we need to wait for the remaining chunks,
所以我们不能就这样离开这里
so we can't just leave here.
我们还要做些工作
We need to go.
给Callback赋值另一个闭包
Callback equals yet another closure,
这将引起对readable函数的二次或多次调用
and that's going to cause a second call or Nth call to this readable function again
我们要在这里重新注册刚才注销的socket
and we'll register that again with a selector to re-register the socket that we unregistered up here
这里的return就没有必要了
and then this return calls no longer necessary.
如果我们运行这个
So if we run this.
我们会看到的
We'll see that.
我们的两个请求现在都完成了
Both of our requests now complete.
这是坠吼的
So that's fantastic,
但不幸的是
but unfortunately.
我们看不到她的最终输出 因为我们在这个死循环里
We don't see her final output because we're in this while true loop,
所以我们被阻塞在这个selector上，因为没有什么可以做的了
so were blocked here on this selector because there's nothing left to do,
但是我们还没有让循环完成
but we haven't told the loop to complete,
如果我们点击这里的停止
and if we hit stop here,
我们会看到的
we'll see that.
我们卡在这行语句上了
This line is, in fact,where we're stuck.
所以我认为结束这个循环的正确方法是 搞清楚任务何时完成，然后退出循环
So I think that the right way to complete this loop now is to somehow figure out when all work is complete and then exit the loop.
所以我设置了任务数这个变量
So I'm going to say that there is some number of tasks.
这个变量贯穿整个执行过程
*That are always in flight.
刚开始时
To begin with,
没有任务在执行
there are none.
一旦我们调用get函数
And whenever we call get.
就会增加任务数
It'll Increment the number of tasks.
当我们读完服务器的响应时
And when we have finished reading a response from a server.
就可以把任务数减1了
Then it's time to decrement it.
所以当我们调用get foo的时候把任务数增加到1
So when we call get foo that increments the tasks to one
当调用get bar 时，任务数又加1
and when we call get bar, that increments it too,
然后
and then,
当回调链都结束时
as each of the chains of callbacks runs to completion,
就将任务数减1
it decrements n_tasks.
直到这个事件循环的n_tasks为零时退出
until this event loop sees that n tasks is zero and quits
如果我们运行这个
If we run this,
然后我们会看到这两个请求都完成了 奇迹般地只花了一秒而不是两秒
then we'll see that both of the requests complete and miraculously it's only taken one second, not two.
我们可以做到
and we can do.
哦
Oops.
更多的并发请求 还是只需要一秒
Many more of these concurrent requests and it will still only take one second.
这样做的原因是服务器太慢了
And the reason for that is that the server is so slow
与从服务器上等待下一个分段的时间相比
that this client is not spending significant CPU processing each of the responses
（本地）客户端不用消耗大量的CPU资源去处理每一个响应
compared to how long its spending waiting for the next chunk from the server.
服务器需要整整1秒才能返回几百字节的数据
The server takes a full second to return just a few hundred bytes of data
而客户端所做的只是将这些数据块插入到一个列表中
and all the client is doing is appending those chunks to a list.
因此 客户端几乎没有CPU开销
So the client is spending almost no CPU
而在绝大多数时间内都是在等待I/O
with spending overwhelmingly the majority of its time waiting for i/o.
这就是异步优化的应用场景
So,this is the sort of thing that async is optimized for.
我们可以用一个简单的框架来做几十个甚至上百个并发的请求
We can do probably dozens or even hundreds of simultaneous requests with a simple framework like this one.
而不用在运算上损失大量的时间
and not lose significant amounts of time on computation,
它非常高效 因为它不需要保持空闲线程就可以达到同样的效果
and it's very efficient because it doesn't have to hold open idle threads In order to do that.
这很好
So that's great.
它非常高效
It's very efficient,
但你也会发现 与简单的初始get函数相比，现在就是一团乱麻
but you'll also see that it's kind of a mess compared to a very simple initial implementation of Get,
我们现在写了一堆乱七八糟的东西
we've now created a whole bunch of mess.
我们现在需要三个函数
We now need three functions where
原来只需要一个
before we only had one.
这三个函数
These three functions.
关于它们的特别之处在于 每当一个函数退出时
What's particularly about about them is that each time a function exits,
它失去了所有的局部变量，例如s、request和chunks
it loses all of its local variables *right so s and request and chunks
当一个回调函数完成时，需要将下一个回调注册到调用链中
each time one of these callbacks completes and registers the next callback in the chain to be executed.
它必须手动将它的状态复制到一个闭包中 这样就可以在调用链的下一个回调中使用这个状态
It has to manually copy its state into a closure so that that state is available to the next call back in the chain.
语言提供给我们的基础设施，比如堆栈和局部变量
The normal facilities that the language provides to us in a stack and in local variables,
在我们的异步框架中，必须手动重新创建它们
we have to manually recreate that stuff in our async framework.
在维持I/O状态时，语言特性对我们来说基本上没有帮助
The language is basically no help to us here in terms of maintaining state across IO operations.
所以问题的解决方案来到了下一个阶段
So the solution to this is the next phase.
协程
It's coroutines.
协程建立在Future类上
And coroutines are built on Future.
这是我们稍后在介绍python生成器时看到的类
Which is a class that we'll see in a second on python generators.
我们稍后将会看到另一个叫做Task的类
And on another class that we'll see in a moment called Task.
现在很多协程的概念
Now there are a bunch of kinds of things called coroutines.
协程这个概念其实很早就有了
coroutines are very old idea.
协程在不同的语言中有不同的实现
There are many kinds of implementations of coroutines in many languages
在Python3的asyncio中
in Python3 asyncio
当我们说协程的时候
what we mean when we say coroutines is,
指的是基于生成器的协程
Generator based coroutines.
Greenlet在Python3.5中也被称作协程
Greenlet are also called coroutines in Python3.5.
现在有了新的原生协程 可以利用新的async和await关键字
There are now new things called native coroutines that can take advantage of the new async and await keywords.
它们本质上是基于生成器的语法糖
They're essentially syntactic sugar on top of generators.
所以如果你理解了我们之后讨论的内容
So if you understand the discussion they were going to have right now,
就能同时了解Python3.5中原生协程的工作方式
you'll understand how the Python3.5 native coroutines work as well,
尽管它们是内置在解释器里而不是直接用生成器写的
although they're built into the interpreter rather than built out of generators,
这是我们现在要做的（用生成器实现）
the way we're going to do right now.
所以
So.
我们首先需要的是一个future类
The first thing that we need is a future class.
稍后，你们会明白为什么它很有用
And you'll see why in a little bit this is useful
我先把它写出来
but for the moment I'm just going to present it,
你现在只需要相信这将会是一个有用的东西
and you'll just have to trust me that this is going to be a useful thing,
future类代表着一些我们正在等待但尚未完成的事件
so a future represents some pending event that we're were waiting for.
它有一个事件发生时将要被执行的回调列表
It has a list of callbacks that will be executed when that event occurs,
当事件发生时，会调用resolve函数，
and when that event occurs, somebody's going to call resolve and the future will.
future类会执行所有等待该事件的回调
Execute all of the callbacks that were waiting for that event.
这就是我们的future类
So that's our future class.
我们要简单地修改代码，而不是直接用selector来注册和回调
And we're going to do this simple transformation where instead of register and callbacks directly with the selector,
我们要注册futures类
we're going to register futures instead.
所以我们将回调添加到future的回调列表中
So we add the callback to the list of callbacks.
等待这个future来执行回调 而不是直接注册回调
waiting for this future to be resolved and instead of registering the callback directly.
我们注册future
We register the future instead.
这里也做相同操作
And I have to do the same thing here.
最后
And finally,
我们必须再做一次麻烦的重构
we have to do that same laborious transformation.
在我们注册回调的三个地方
in the three places where we had registered callbacks,
我们现在给futures加入回调，并对futures进行了注册
we're now adding callbacks to futures and registering the future instead.
这意味着在我们的事件循环中
And that means that down here in our event loop.
data不再是回调，而是future对象
The event that data is no longer a callback its future,
所以我们不直接调用它
and so we don't call it directly.
而是调用它的resolve方法
Instead,we say future.resolve.
所以你可以预测一下
So, you can expect,
进行简单的修改之后，很可能得到正确的结果
with such a simple transformation that had probably got it right,
看上去我做到了
and it looks like I did so.
到目前为止，我们所做的一切都把代码变的又杂乱又冗长
All we've done so far is made our code even worse,  even more messy and long,
程序的性能和之前的一样
and we have simply got the same performance that we had before.
所以下一步就是用future类和生成器来实现协程
So the next step is going to be to somehow use these futures with generators to start to implement coroutines.
所以我要快速复习一下生成器
So I'm going to do a quick little refresher about Generators.
生成器有一些难以理解的特性
cause there's a few confusing things about them.
即使对经验丰富的python程序员来说也是如此
Even for veteran python programs.
生成器是用生成器函数创建的
So a generator is created with a generator function
生成器函数是任何包含的yield表达式的函数
and a generator function is any function that contains the yield statement.
所以这个生成器函数将会打印start和1
So this generator function is going to print start yield one.
Middle
Middle.
还有2
Two.
最后打印done
And then it's done.
生成器函数的有趣之处在于 当你执行它时
And the funny thing about a generator function is that when you execute it,
它实际上并没有运行它的代码
it doesn't actually run its code.
它没有打印start middle或done
It didn't print start middle or done
而是创建了一个生成器对象
Instead,it created a generator object
这个生成器对象包含一个代码对象,即用来表示这些内容的字节码（co_code）
and this generator object contains a code object *that's the byte code that represents this stuff.
然后
And?
它有44个字节
It's got forty four bytes
生成器自身也有一个栈帧
and the generator also has a stack frame.
它有一个指令指针
And that's got an instruction pointer,
初始值为-1
and it begins his negative one,
也就是说它还没有执行任何指令
meaning that it hasn't executed any instructions yet.
这就是为什么我们没有看到这些print语句的输出
And that's why we didn't actually see any of these prints statements is being executed.
运行一个生成器的方法是对它调用next函数
So the way to run a generator is to call him next on it.
如果你这样做
And if you do that,
然后你会看到它执行了最初的一些字节码
then you'll see that it executes its first few bites of byte code,
所以它打印start
so it prints start
1 实际上是next语句的返回值
and one is actually the return value of the next statement
因为next()的返回值由next执行的yield语句决定
because the return value of next is whichever yield is next executed.
现在 指令指针暂停在第13个字节处
And the instruction pointer is now paused at thirteen bites into the forty four bytes of bytecode.
所以如果我们再次调用next
So if we call next again
我要保存它的返回值 这样你就能看到它打印出middle
this time,I'm going to assign its return value so that you can see that a prints middle.
但它返回2
But it returns two.
这是下一个yield语句传递出的值
Which was the value passed into the next yield statement.
现在我们的堆栈指针(口误)
And now our stack pointer....
对不起
Sorry,
我们的指示指针来到第28字节
our instruction pointer is at twenty eight of forty four.
如果我们再次调用next
And if we call next one more time.
然后我们将看到停止迭代异常
Then we'll raise stop iteration exception,
这说明
which indicates that
它已经完成了 lasti指针已经被删除了
It's done executing and the lasti pointer has actually been deleted.
这就是生成器如何在Python2.5及之前版本的中工作的
So that's how a generator works in all versions of Python going back two point five.
那么我们如何用它来实现协程呢
So how do we use that to create a coroutine?
嗯
Well,
先做一个设想
here's the promise.
我们的想法是这样的
The promise is going to be that.
这个get函数
This get function.
需要创建一个闭包 以捕获他的局部变量
Which currently has to create a closure that captures his local variables.
将其命名为callback
Names that closure callback.
向future增加回调 然后注册future到selector
adds that callback to the future and then registers that future with the selector.
这个回调完全可以简化
This can be simplified to not require a call back at all.
所以我要删除回调
So I'm going to delete the callback.
删除回调主体
I'm going to delete the callbacks body.
但我们需要暂停直至socket可写
But we need to pause until s is writable
在我们注销它之前，这里是可写的。当socket可写时，就可以调用send
somehow here before we unregistered it and then rely on the socket to be writable so that we can call send on it
我们的想法是
and the promise is that somehow,
通过yield f
by yielding F,
这个我们刚刚创建的future对象
the future that we just created.
我们可以用某种方式暂停这个生成器 直到我们感兴趣的事件发生
Somehow we can pause this generator until the event that we said we were interested in has occurred.
如果我们认为这个设想可行
And if we believe that this promise is true.
然后 我们可以将两个函数合并成包含yield语句的单一生成器函数
Then we can combine what had been two functions into a single generator function that contains a yield statement.
但这个设想还没有实现,因为如果我运行这个
But the promise is not going to be fulfilled just yet because if I run this,
它将花费0秒
it's going to take zero seconds.
它没有输出
It has no output,
没有实现想要的效果
and it doesn't do any work.
为什么呢
So why is that?
这里发生了什么
What happened here?
嗯
Well,
回想一下 当你执行一个生成器函数时
recall that when you execute a generator function,
它会返回生成器，实际上并不运行它的任何代码
it returns a generator doesn't actually run any of its code.
现在我在这里添加了一个yield语句
So now that I've added a yield statement here to get,
这意味着这里的get语句
that means that get here.
只返回了一个生成器
Just returns a generator.
实际上什么都没做
doesn't actually do anything,
这里也是一样
and the same here.
那么我们要怎么执行它呢
So how are we going to execute it?
如何对它执行next方法呢
How do we call next on it?
这就是这个基于协程的异步框架的第三个部分：Task类
So that is the third piece of this puzzle of this coroutine based async framework is the task class.
Task类
Task class.
它负责在生成器上调用next
It's responsible for calling next on generators.
我们来看看它是什么样的
So let's see what that looks like.
同时使用future和task类时
And in the case of both future and task,
现在写的这些内容非常简单，或者说过于简单了，而且实现并不完善
these are incredibly simple and oversimplified and buggy incomplete implementations of these ideas.
不过这些想法在许多框架中得到了充分体现
These ideas are fully expressed in a number of frameworks,
尤其是tornado和python3.4标准库中的asyncio
notably tornado and now in asyncio in the python3.4 standard library.
所以我的丐版Task类的实现如下：
So my dumb version of the task class is going to look like.
我们将用生成器初始化它
We're going to initialize it with a generator.
我将保存它
I will save that.
然后我们会有一个叫做Step的函数
And then we'll have a function called Step,
这个术语是从asyncio那里借来的
and this terminology is borrowed from a asyncio.
step函数的任务就是在生成器上调用next
What step does his calls next on the generator.
生成器将会yield一个future对象
And since the generator,
it's going to yield a future.
这就变成了next()的返回值
So that's going to become the return value of next.
我们来捕获它
So let's capture that.
然后
And then.
当这个future执行完回调时 我们想要达成什么目的？
What do we want to happen when this future is resolved?
我们需要给future增加一些回调
We need to add some kind of callback to the future,
这是我们想要在future就绪时执行的动作
something that we want to happen once the future is ready
让我们把self.step作为回调
and let's just pass self dot step in as the callback.
所以一旦这个future完成之后
So once this future is resolved,
就会回到这里 然后再次对self.gen执行next
we'll just come right back into here and we'll call next and self.gen again.
当再次对self.gen执行next时
when we call next on self.gen again,
程序这将在这里恢复执行
that's going to resume here.
因此我们知道我们可以注销socket文件号
And therefore we know that we can unregister the sockets file number,
现在socket是可写的
and that s is now writable.
所以如果我们运行它 它仍然不会起作用
So if we run this still not going to work.
原因是
The reason for that is.
我们需要对self.step做一个初始的调用
That we need to make an initial call the self.step,
我们给self.gen做了一个初始的调用(预激)这样我们就启动了get函数
so that we make an initial call to self.gen so that we get the get function started,
它会连接socket 等等
and it will connect the socket and so on.
我们在这里改一下
So let's just do that right here.
在构造函数中
In the constructor.
然后是这个修改的最后一步，下面这里
And then the final step of this conversion is going to be down here,
我们需要用task把这些get调用包起来
where we need to wrap each of these calls in a task
当get返回一个生成器时，task对象会把它包起来
so when get returns a generator, the task wraps it
保存到self.gen中，然后调用self.step
Signs it to self.gen and calls self.step
之后就会调用next，真正地执行代码直至第一个yield语句
and that will call next and that will actually begin this thing executing up until the first yield statement
如果我运行这个
So if I run this.
在某种程度上
In a way,
你会看到我们已经有些进步了
you will see the way we make progress.
因为我们在这里抛出了一个停止迭代异常
Because we raise a stop iteration exception here.
所以这确实是个好消息
So that that actually that's good news,
因为这意味着这个get生成器实际上已经运行到结束了
because it means that this get generator has actually been run to completion.
它完成了它所要做的工作
It's done the work that it set out to do.
所以
so.
如果我们
if we.
catch一下异常
Catch that.
我们想在这里做什么
What do we want to do here?
嗯
Well,
task完成了
the task is done.
直接返回
So let's just return.
如果我们执行这个版本
And if we execute this version.
实际上已经成功了
It actually completes.
吼啊 我们还有一些零散的回调
So this is fantastic now we've still got a few stray callbacks.
所以
So.
我们可以删去这些，在这里做同样的修改
We can get rid of those the same transformation that we did here.
所以在这里做同样的操作
So we're just going to do it down here again as well,
所以我们要
so we're going to.
我们再也不需要这个调用了
We don't need this call back any more.
你不需要把它加到future中
You don't need to add it to the future.
我们仍然需要说明我们关注的事件，并注册future对象
We do still need to say what event we're interested in and register the future to be resolved when that event occurs,
但是我们可以删除回调定义
but we can delete the callback definition.
因为我们在之前的同一个函数中
Since we're still in the same function as we were in before,
我们不需要一个冗余的全局声明
we don't need a redundant global statement.
如果我们简单地yield我们新定义的future
And if we simply yield this new future that we created,
这意味着
that means that.
到目前为止
By now,
当task恢复的时候
by the time the task resolve.. resumes us,
这个socket现在是可读的
the socket is now readable.
这是最后一个回调
And here we've got our last of the callback.
我们可以把它删掉
so we can delete that.
我们可以yield我们的future 而不是注册一个回调
And we can yield our future instead of registering a callback.
当我们收到下一个分块时 我们要做什么
What do we want to do once we have received the next chunk?
换句话说
In other words,
当socket再次处于可读状态
once the socket is readable again?
我们想要得到下一个分块，对吧？
we want to receive the next chunk right？
所以我们最后要做的是
so what we're going to end up doing is
借鉴在教程刚开始的时候写的死循环
we're going to end up reproducing the same while true loop that we originally had in the olden days at the beginning of this talk,
那时我们只写了一个简单的阻塞get函数
when we were writing a simple blocking get.
所以它看起来是这样的
So that's going to look something like.
我们要把这个放在循环中
We're going to put this within the loop.
每次执行循环时
And each time through the loop we say,
我想从socket上读取数据
I want to read from the socket,
所以等待这个future执行完毕
so wait for this future to be resolved.
然后从selector中注销socket
And then unregistered the socket from the selector.
得到当前的分块
get the chunk.
如果有分块，那就加入到列表中 这个部分是多余的
And if there is any then added to the list and this stuff is now extra.
这个循环会重复 在这里重复做这些
The loop will just repeat and do that stuff again up here,
如果没有分块
and if there's no chunk.
这意味着
That means that.
我们已经接收完服务器响应
We're done reading the server response,
所以我们可以
and so we can.
连接各个分块
Join the body up,
打印第一行 减去任务数
print the first line decrement the tasks count,
从现在开始 我们又回到了一个无限循环
and since now we're in an infinite loop again.
在这里 我们需要立即返回
here we need to return as soon as we're done.
现在
Now,
如果一切顺利 我运行这个
if all goes well and I run this,
它仍然只花了一秒
then it still takes one second.
它还是做了所有的工作
it still does all the work that it was asked to do
我们可以把它扩展到能够执行大量的任务而不损失任何性能
and we can still scale this out to a large number of tasks without any loss of performance,
因为发起10个或15个协程的资源消耗实在是太低廉了
because launching ten fifteen coroutines is incredibly cheap,
大概只和一堆回调差不多
it's roughly as cheap as a bunch of callbacks.
所以协程同时拥有回调和线程的长处
So coroutines are kind of the best of both worlds.
资源消耗和回调一样少，比线程更是不知道少到哪里去了
they're about as cheap as callbacks they're much cheaper than threads
我在我的系统上测量了一个协程..
on my system, I measured that a coroutine takes...
大约需要6K的内存，而线程需要30K
About six K of memory versus about thirty K of memory for a thread,
此外 我做了一个小实验：我有可以启动超过十万个协程
and furthermore I did a little experiment and found that I was capable of launching over a hundred thousand coroutines.
它们的限制仅仅是Python进程允许分配的内存总量
Their limited only by the amount of ram that the Python process is allowed to allocate.
对比线程
versus Threads,
除了简单的内存限制之外 线程还受到其他限制
which are subject to other limits beside simply memory limits.
各种用户和操作系统限制了一个进程被允许启动线程数量
There are various user and operating system limits on the number of threads that a *process is allowed to start with.
这个问题在很多情况下都很难解决
which are difficult in various ways to work around,
线程占用空间和操作系统的数据结构，以及操作系统调度器
and they take up space and operating system data structures and the operating system scheduler
最终导致它们的开销变得非常大
that eventually causes their overhead to become quite significant.
他们所做的一切只是在等待一些缓慢的I/O操作。这实际上不需要非常多的CPU资源
All they're doing is waiting around for some sort of slow IO operations that aren't actually going to require very much CPU。
相较于协程在这个程序中的应用
so compared to coroutines for a application like this,
这将花费很少的时间用于CPU计算
that's going to spend very little time doing computation
并且绝大多数时间都花在等待一个缓慢的服务器或者 客户端的缓慢socket上
and overwhelmingly spending its time waiting for a slow server or a slow client at the other end of the socket.
在这种情况下协程有效率的多
Coroutines are much more efficient for this kind of thing,
但是和回调相比 它们的简单得多 因为
but compared to call backs their lot simpler because.
你可以把协程的所有的代码放在一个函数里
You can put all of the code for a coroutine in one function,
所以你不需要声明并注册整个调用链
so you don't have to declare and register a whole chain of callbacks.
你可以重复使用你的局部变量 就像你原来的习惯
And you can just reuse your local variables the same way that  you have always done.
这就是Tornado或asyncio风格，这些基于协程的异步框架的开端。
So that's the beginning of Tornado style or async i/o style coroutine based async framework.
如果你想了解更多
So if you want to know more about this,
访问bit.ly/coroutines 我创建了一个页面
go to bit.ly/coroutines so I've have created a landing page for you there
你可以在那里看到我刚才写的代码
that'll link you out to a version of the code that I wrote just now,
那里也可以看到我和Guido(Python之父)合写的一章
as well as link you to a chapter that I wrote with Guido van Rossum
这章将会出现在开源应用程序架构系列的下一本书中
that will appear in the next book in the architecture of Open source Application series.
这一章深入地介绍了在Python3.4的标准库中，基于生成器的协程的实现细节
and that chapter goes into far more detail about how generator based coroutines are implemented in asyncio on Python3.4 standard library,
特别是它详细描述协程如何利用基于python3的生成器特性
and especially it goes into how coroutines take advantage of generator features that are specific to python3
以及asyncio库中如何运用异步队列类
and how a asynchronous queue class that's included in asyncio,
以一种惯用线程的工作者非常熟悉的方式来使用协程
can be used to coordinate coroutines in a way that's very familiar to people who are used to using threads.
提醒一下
And as a reminder,
如果你想和我这样的人在一家开源公司工作
if you want to work with people like me at a opensource company,
非常热情、多元、充实以及有技术挑战的工作
that's very warm and diversity has really fulfilling and technically challenging jobs.
Mongodb正在招聘
Mongo db is hiring.
我们在纽约的帕罗奥多和世界各地都设有办事处
We have offices in New York in Palo Alto and worldwide.
访问bit.ly/mongo-jobs
Go to bit.ly/mongo-jobs.
我将很荣幸与你共事
I would love to work with you.